Mss.B.J44 Mss.B.J44
American Philosophical Society
H. S. (Herbert Spencer) Jennings papers, ca. 1893-1947
Circa 1893-1947
Mss.B.J44
American Philosophical Society
14.5 Linear feet
This is a diverse collection, including correspondence, drafts of letters, notes and notebooks (on biometric methods; tables and formulae; science, nature and method; coefficient and correlation; vitalism; Japanese language); commonplace book (1924); autobiography; and over one hundred folders of unpublished writings. The correspondence and other material covers a variety of topics, including biology, eugenics, evolution and natural selection, human heredity, paramecia, protozoa genetics, U.S. immigration policy. There is much on the Seventh International Congress of Zoology (1907); letters to his father and wives, and from students and colleagues on his seventy-fifth birthday, 1943 (1 v.); diplomas and certificates of membership; and photographs.
Ca. 7000 items
Ca. 7000 items, 14.5 linear ft.
Jennings, H. S., (Herbert Spencer), 1868-1947
Box 1-29
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Mrs. Vernon Lynch, Burridge Jennings, Carolyn Jennings, S. W. Geiser, and Tracy M. Sonneborn, 1947-1977. See in-house shelf for additional accession numbers and dates.
Biographical/Historical note
Herbert Spencer Jennings (1868-1947, APS 1907) was a microbiologist, zoologist and geneticist. In his critical monograph Contributions to the Study of the Behavior of Lower Organisms (1904) Jennings challenged the theory physicochemical tropisms in animals championed by Jacques Loeb (1859-1924, APS 1899), and brought single-celled organisms into the realm of psychology. He also helped to found the field of mathematical genetics by systematically applying principles of Mendelian theory to his calculations of expectable ratios of the traits in various types of inheritance. Jennings’s most important contribution to genetics was his investigation of the questions of variation and evolution that confirmed the gradual but persistent progress of the latter by the accrual of very slight alterations.
Jennings was born on April 8, 1868, the son of physician George Nelson Jennings and Olive Taft Jenks, in Tonica, Illinois. He learned to read at a very early age, by delving into his father’s extensive home library. From 1874-1879 the family lived in various localities in California, before returning to Tonica, Illinois, where Jennings attended a public high school. After high school, he studied at the Illinois Normal School near Bloomington (now Illinois State University) in 1887-88, then briefly taught in rural schools near his home in Tonica. At the age of twenty-one in 1889 without a degree, Jennings served as assistant professor of botany and horticulture at the Agricultural and Mechanical College of Texas (later Texas A & M University).
In 1890 Jennings matriculated at the University of Michigan, where he studied with the young zoologist and ichthyologist Jacob Reighard. He graduated with a B.S. in 1893. After a year of graduate study at Michigan, Jennings moved on to Harvard to study with Reighard’s mentor Edward Laurens Mark at the Zoological Laboratory. He received an M.A. from Harvard in 1895 and a Ph.D. in 1896. His thesis was on the embryology of a rotifer. As a graduate student, Jennings was influenced by Charles Benedict Davenport (1866-1944, APS 1907), then a Harvard instructor, to shift his interests from descriptive to experimental biology. After completing his doctorate, Jennings was awarded the Parker traveling fellowship, which allowed him during the winter of 1896-97 to study the response of the Paramecium to stimuli with pioneering researcher on protozoan behavior Max Verworn at the University of Jena. In the spring of 1897 Jennings worked at the Naples Zoological Laboratory. Returning home that summer, he held several one-year appointments as professor of botany at the Montana State Agricultural and Mechanical College (1897-98) and as instructor in zoology at Dartmouth (1898-99) to replace a professor on leave. Also in 1898 Jennings wed Mary Louise Burridge, an artist and a son born to them later that year.
In 1899 Jennings became a zoology instructor at the University of Michigan, progressing to the rank of assistant professor in 1901. Also, in 1901 he coauthored a textbook with Reighard, entitled the Anatomy of the Cat. During his summers at the University of Michigan, Jennings continued to serve under Reighard’s supervision as an assistant with the Michigan lake surveys. In 1902 he was appointed program director for the U.S. Fish Commission Biological Survey of the Great Lakes.
In 1903 Jennings became assistant professor of zoology at the University of Pennsylvania and was allowed a one-year leave to return to the Naples Zoological Laboratory, funded by a grant from the Carnegie Institution. He published the results of his research the following year as Contributions to the Study of the Behavior of Lower Organisms (1904). In 1906 Jennings moved on to Johns Hopkins University to become professor of experimental zoology. Here he was assigned light teaching duties and provided with a laboratory. In 1910 he was promoted to become Henry Walters Professor of Zoology and directed the zoological laboratory until his retirement in 1938.
Even before his post-doctoral studies, Jennings pursued experimental research on the behavior of primitive animals and their reactions to stimuli. Of his many published papers, Jennings’s study of “The Psychology of a Protozoan” (1899) sparked the strongest reaction. He had become greatly interested in the complex behavior of these single-celled microorganisms, which he attributed to their entire structure. These views drew fire from University of Chicago biologist Jacques Loeb, who maintained the reactions of all life forms could ultimately be explained as physical or chemical reactions [i.e. tropisms]. However, at a scientific meeting in 1900 Jennings provided experimental demonstrations to prove the validity of his theory, and obtained the agreement of Loeb.
In 1900 Jennings was one of the many biologists inspired to study genetics by the rediscovery of Gregor Mendel’s work on inheritance in plants. In his laboratory at Johns Hopkins he began to study the genetics and evolution of two species of single-celled organisms, the Paramecium and Difflugia. His goal was to discover the origin of hereditary variations in organisms, whose reproduction is primarily asexual. Jennings based his research on the characteristics of individual organisms (aggregating these results statistically, rather than studying them as groups). He discovered that the progeny of the individual organisms were identical with the “parent” organisms. Further studies by Jennings’s graduate students showed that the same is true of multicellular organisms, reproducing by asexual means. Systematically applying Mendelian theory to his samples, he helped to found the field of mathematical genetics by calculating the expectable ratios of traits in various types of inheritance. Jennings’s greatest contriubutions to genetics related to questions of variation and evolution. From 1908 to 1916 Jennings and his students published a number of papers, discussing the constancy and variability of traits in protozoan lines of inheritance. He demonstrated that within a given species there are a number of particular strains whose traits endure for many generations. However, he also noticed the spontaneous development of very slight, but persistent variations. The net effect of his work was to modify the theory of mutations, since the alterations he observed were so slight that they suggested evolution proceeded gradually by means of very small (rather than abrupt) changes. A contemporary university publication offered a somewhat exaggerated description of Jennings as the first scientific researcher “to actually see and control the process of evolution among living things.”
After Jennings’s appointment as Director of Johns Hopkins zoological laboratory, he had less time to spend on his own research, but continued to supervise the work of graduate students. He also produced an important series of writings that popularized genetics and discussed the philosophical implications of the new methods and findings of experimental biology. His popular books, that included Life and Death: Heredity and Evolution in Unicellular Organisms (1920), Prometheus; or, Biology and the Advancement of Man (1925), The Biological Basis of Human Nature (1930) and The Universe and Life (1933) focused on the central finding of his lifework that biological processes are identical across the animal kingdom. In 1935 he also authored a textbook entitled Genetics.
In 1938 his wife Mary died, shortly after Jennings’s retirement from Johns Hopkins, and the following spring he accepted a position as visiting professor at the University of California at Los Angeles. There at the age of seventy he resumed his research on the Paramecium, about which he published several new papers. In 1939 he married Lulu Plant Jennings, his brother’s widow.
Throughout his career Jennings held memberships and offices in many scientific societies and learned organizations. He was elected to the American Philosophical Society in 1907. He was also a member of the American Zoological Society (President, 1908-09), the Philadelphia Academy of Natural Sciences, the American Society of Naturalists (1910-11) and a fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences (in 1914). Internationally, Jennings was an honorary fellow of the Royal Microscopical Society in Great Britain, a member of the Royal Society of Edinburgh, a member of the Société de Biologie de Paris and a corresponding member of the Russian Academy of Science.
In addition to his many scholarly and popular books on biology and genetics, Jennings published numerous papers in zoological and physiological journals. He was also the Associate Editor of the Journal of Experimental Zoology and Genetics and of the Biological Bulletin.
Jennings spent his final years in Los Angeles, California. He died in Santa Monica, California on April 14, 1947.
Naval History Note
The Jennings Papers contain at least one item which may be of interest to naval historians:
Navy Department Intelligence Office, 11th Naval District. Letter to Herbert S. Jennings. 1945 February 26. Asking for information on his foreign residence. 1 page.
Physiology, Biochemistry, and Biophysics Note
Scholars of physiology, biochemistry, or biophysics may find the following items of interest:
Lillie, Frank Rattray, 1870-1947 ( Includes correspondence regarding Marine Biological Laboratory, Woods Hole; National Research Council; National Academy of Sciences.) Correspondence (42 items) 1905-1935 English
Loeb, Jacques, 1859-1924 Correspondence (5 items) 1920 English
Genetics Note
This collection contains materials which relate to the history of genetics.
Brenneman, Joseph Correspondence (89 items) 1892-1939
Carnegie Institution of Washington Correspondence (5 folders) 1902-1905
Chen, T. T. Correspondence (47 items) 1936-1940
Conklin, Edward G. Correspondence (34 items) 1904-1940
Davenport, Charles Benedict Correspondence (40 items) 1899-1930
Geiser, Samuel W. Correspondence (92 items) 1924-1975
Goodnow, Frank J. Correspondence (58 items) 1918-1924
Harrison, Ross Correspondence (73 items) 1904-1944
Henry Holt and Company Correspondence (30 items) 1900-1945
International Congress of Zoology. Seventh Congress Records (196 items) 1907
Jennings, Herbert Spencer -- Commonplace book Notebooks (1 volume) 1924-1945
Jennings, Herbert Spencer -- Diaries Diaries (16 volumes) 1903-1945
Jennings, Herbert Spencer -- Scrapbooks Scrapbooks (10 volumes) 1931-1932, 1935-1937
Jennings, Herbert Spencer -- Problems of Life, Age, and Death Manuscripts (Approximately 200 pages) 1943
Jennings, Herbert Spencer -- Vitalism Correspondence (12 letters) 1909-1915
Jennings, Herbert Spencer -- Works by Jennings Manuscripts (Approximately 100 folders) 1868-1945
Jennings, Mary Louise Burridge Correspondence (166 items) 1894-1936
Journal of Experimental Zoology Correspondence (44 items) 1904-1941
Kornhauser, S. I. Correspondence (30 items) 1919-1924
Korzybski, Alfred Correspondence (27 items) 1922-1939
Joseph Leidy Award Correspondence (26 items) 1923-1925
Lillie, Frank Rattray Correspondence (44 items) 1905-1935
Lovejoy, Arthur O. Correspondence (22 items) 1919-1928
Lynch, Ruth Stocking Correspondence (81 items) 1920-1948
Mast, Samuel Ottmar Correspondence (40 items) 1904-1945
Montana State College Correspondence (33 items) 1933-1935
Morgan, Thomas Hunt Correspondence (23 items) 1907-1924
National Research Council Correspondence (31 items) 1918-1940
Neal, Herbert V. Correspondence (36 items) 1897-1934
Norton, W. W. and Company Correspondence (82 items) 1930-1945
Pearl, Raymond Correspondence (278 items) 1899-1933
Reighard, Jacob Correspondence (29 items) 1897-1933
Shull, George Harrison Correspondence (72 items) 1918-1923
Sonneborn, Tracy M. Correspondence (163 items) 1926-1973
Williams and Wilkins Company Correspondence (56 items) 1918-1936
Wilson, Edwin Bidwell Correspondence (9 items) 1920-1959
Yerkes, Robert M. Correspondence (46 items) 1899-1940
Young, Aldie Jennings Manuscripts (10 items) 1895-1897, 1934
Scope and Contents note
A diversified collection of great size. Includes correspondence, miscellaneous papers, diaries, manuscripts (many unpublished), notebooks, lecture notes, syllabi of courses taught by Jennings at Johns Hopkins University, scrapbooks, memorabilia, etc. Correspondents in the Jennings papers include: T. T. Chen (reserarch assistant), Samuel W. Geiser (graduate student), Arthur O. Lovejoy (colleague), Ruth Stocking Lynch (graduate student and research assistant), Samuel Ottmar Mast (graduate student and colleague), and Tracy M. Sonneborn (graduate student and colleague).
Other Finding Aids note
The printed version of Bentley Glass' A Guide to the Genetics Collections of the American Philosophical Society contains another biography of Jennings and a further description of the Jennings Papers.
Alexander, Jerome, b. 1876; Aydelotte, Frank, 1880-1956; Blumer, Herbert, 1900-1987; Brennemann, Joseph, 1872-1944; Burbank, Luther, 1849-1926; Calkins, Gary N., (Gary Nathan), b. 1869; Cattell, James McKeen, 1860-1944; Chen, Tze-tuan, 1906-; Conklin, Edwin Grant, 1863-1952; Cowdry, E. V., (Edmund Vincent), 1888-1975; Davenport, Charles Benedict, 1866-1944; Fisher, Irving, 1867-1947; Geiser, Samuel Wood, 1890-1983; Harrison, Ross G., (Ross Granville), 1870-1959; Kellogg, Vernon L., (Vernon Lyman), 1867-1937; Korzybski, Alfred, 1879-1950; Lillie, Frank Rattray, 1870-1947; Mast, Samuel Ottmar, 1871-1947; Metcalf, Maynard M., (Maynard Mayo), 1868-1940; Metz, Carl W., 1889-1975; Muller, H. J., (Hermann Joseph), 1890-1967; Osterud, Hjalmar Laurits, b. 1883; Pearl, Raymond, 1879-1940; Pomeroy, Fred Elmer, b. 1877; Raffel, Daniel, b. 1899; Shull, George Harrison, 1874-1954; Sonneborn, T.M., (Tracy Morton), 1905-1981; Vavilov, N. I. (Nikolai Ivanovich), 1887-1943; Watson, John B., (John Broadus), 1878-1958; Whitney, Leon Fradley, 1894-; Wilson, Edwin Bidwell, 1879-1964; Yerkes, Robert Mearns, 1876-1956; Animal behavior.; Autobiographies.; Biology.; Biometry.; Certificates.; Commonplace books.; Correlation (Statistics); Diplomas.; Emigration and immigration law -- United States.; Eugenics.; Evolution.; Genetics.; Heredity.; Japanese language; Lectures.; Natural selection.; Notebooks.; Paramecium -- Physiology.; Photoprints.; Protozoa -- Physiology.; Vitalism.; Zoologists -- United States.
- Selected Inventory from Genetics Subject Guide
  - Brenneman, Joseph, 1892-1939; Correspondence ( 89 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Davenport, Charles Benedict; Educational matters; Harvard University; Huxley, Julian; Lillie, Frank Rattray; Poetry and literature; Travel -- Germany; Travel -- Italy; Travel -- Japan; Travel--California; University of Michigan; Zoology
  - Carnegie Institution of Washington, 1902-1905; Correspondence ( 5 folders )
    Protozoan genetics -- Protozoan behavior; Publication; Research support; Travel -- Italy
  - Chen, T. T., 1936-1940; Correspondence ( 47 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Cytogenetics; Fellowships, assistantships; Protozoan genetics; Publication; Recommendations; Research support
  - Conklin, Edward G., 1904-1940; Correspondence ( 34 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Invitations; Marine Biological Laboratory, Woods Hole; Naples Zoological Station; National Academy of Sciences; Pearl, Raymond; Publication; Weinstein, Alexander
  - Davenport, Charles Benedict, 1899-1930; Correspondence ( 40 items )
    Castle, William Ernest; Conferences and symposia; Genetics -- Goats; Human genetics; International Congress of Eugenics; Johns Hopkins University; Morgan, Thomas Hunt; National Academy of Sciences; National Research Council; Publication; Recommendations; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs; Statistics, biostatistics, biometrics; World War I -- Impact on science
  - Geiser, Samuel W., 1924-1975; Correspondence ( 92 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Drosophila genetics; Johns Hopkins University; Poultry genetics; Protozoan genetics; Publication
  - Goodnow, Frank J., 1918-1924; Correspondence ( 58 items )
    Business; Carribbean research; Driesch, Hans; Fellowships, assistantships; Johns Hopkins University; Marine Biological Laboratory, Woods Hole; Publication; Referee's report; Research support; Teaching; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements; World War I -- Impact on science
  - Harrison, Ross, 1904-1944; Correspondence ( 73 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Editorial matters -- Journal of Experimental Zoology; Eugenics; International Congress of Eugenics; Johns Hopkins University; National Academy of Sciences; National Research Council; Publication; Recommendations; Referee's report -- Kammerer, Paul; Research support; World War I -- Goldschmidt, Richard Benedict; Zoology
  - Henry Holt and Company, 1900-1945; Correspondence ( 30 items )
    Business; Publication
  - Jennings, Herbert Spencer
    - Commonplace book, 1924-1945; Notebooks ( 1 volume ); Jennings, H. S., (Herbert Spencer), 1868-1947
      Biographical and personal data
    - Diaries, 1903-1945; Diaries ( 16 volumes ); Jennings, H. S., (Herbert Spencer), 1868-1947
      Biographical and personal data; Johns Hopkins University; Lectures, public speaking -- Oxford University; Lectures, public speaking -- Princeton University; Lectures, public speaking -- University of California, Los Angeles; Lectures, public speaking -- Yale University; Marine Biological Laboratory, Woods Hole; Teaching; Travel -- Great Britain; Travel -- Japan; Travel -- Lisbon; Travel -- Mediterranean Sea; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; World War I -- Impact on science
    - Problems of Life, Age, and Death, 1943; Manuscripts ( Approximately 200 pages ); Jennings, H. S., (Herbert Spencer), 1868-1947
      Indiana University--Patten Lectures; Lectures, public speaking; Philosophy of science; Protozoan genetics; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Zoology
    - Scrapbooks, 1931-1932, 1935-1937; Scrapbooks ( 10 volumes ); Jennings, H. S., (Herbert Spencer), 1868-1947
      Biographical and personal data; Travel -- Japan; Travel -- Mediterranean Sea; Travel -- Oxford
    - Vitalism, 1909-1915; Correspondence ( 12 letters ); Jennings, H. S., (Herbert Spencer), 1868-1947
      Driesch, Hans; Ethical issues -- Indeterminism; Lovejoy, Arthur O.; Philosophy of science -- Vitalism; Uexkull, Jakob von; Woodruff, Charles
    - Works by Jennings, 1868-1945; Manuscripts ( Approximately 100 folders ); Jennings, H. S., (Herbert Spencer), 1868-1947
      Behavioral genetics, IQ; Bibliographical matters; Biographical and personal data; Biographical and personal data -- Pearl, Raymond; Cytogenetics; Ethical issues; Eugenics; Evolution; Genetics; Genetics of plants; Human genetics; Lectures, public speaking; Philosophy of science; Population, demography; Protozoan genetics; Statistics, biostatistics, biometrics; Travel -- Japan; Travel -- Oxford; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Zoology -- Animal behavior
  - Jennings, Mary Louise Burridge, 1894-1936; Correspondence ( 166 items )
    Art; Biographical and personal data; Fellowships, assistantships; Graduate study -- Harvard University; Music; Poetry and literature; Protozoan genetics; Travel -- Germany; Travel -- Italy; Zoology -- Rotifera
  - Journal of Experimental Zoology, 1904-1941; Correspondence ( 44 items )
    Business; Editorial matters; Publication -- Journal of Experimental Zoology; Referee's report
  - Kornhauser, S. I., 1919-1924; Correspondence ( 30 items )
    Biographical and personal data -- Mark, Edward Laurens; Evolution
  - Korzybski, Alfred, 1922-1939; Correspondence ( 27 items )
    Philosophy of science
  - Joseph Leidy Award, 1923-1925; Correspondence ( 26 items )
    Biographical and personal data; History of biology, especially genetics; Honors -- Joseph Leidy Award
  - Lillie, Frank Rattray, 1905-1935; Correspondence ( 44 items )
    Business; Marine Biological Laboratory, Woods Hole; National Academy of Sciences; National Research Council; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs
  - Loeb, Jacques, 1920; Correspondence ( 5 items )
  - Lovejoy, Arthur O., 1919-1928; Correspondence ( 22 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Congratulations, greetings, thanks; Evolution; Johns Hopkins University; Kammerer, Paul; Lectures, public speaking -- Jennings, Herbert Spencer; World War I -- Impact on science
  - Lynch, Ruth Stocking, 1920-1948; Correspondence ( 81 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Congratulations, greetings, thanks; Jennings, Herbert Spencer -- Death; Johns Hopkins University -- Mast, Samuel Ottmar; Johns Hopkins University -- Sonneborn, Tracy M.; Protozoan genetics; Publication; University of California, Los Angeles -- Chen, T. T.; World War I -- Impact on science
  - Mast, Samuel Ottmar, 1904-1945; Correspondence ( 40 items )
    Graduate study -- Harvard University; Haldane, John Burdon Sanderson; Johns Hopkins University -- Business; Johns Hopkins University -- Graduate study; Johns Hopkins University -- Recommendations; Marine Biological Laboratory, Woods Hole; Oxford University; Protozoan genetics; Publication; Sonneborn, Tracy M.; Spemann, Hans
  - Montana State College, 1933-1935; Correspondence ( 33 items )
    Biographical and personal data -- Jennings, Herbert Spencer
  - Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1907-1924; Correspondence ( 23 items )
    Genetics of plants; International Congress of Eugenics; International Congress of Genetics; Kammerer, Paul; Naples Zoological Station; National Academy of Sciences; Protozoan genetics; Publication; Recommendations; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs; World War I -- Impact on science
  - National Research Council, 1918-1940; Correspondence ( 31 items )
    Committee activities; Educational matters; Fellowships, assistantships; International Union of Biological Societies; National Research Council; Recommendations; Rockefeller Foundation; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs; World War I -- Impact on science
  - Neal, Herbert V., 1897-1934; Correspondence ( 36 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Carnegie Institution of Washington; Davenport, Charles Benedict; Educational matters; Graduate study -- Harvard University; Johns Hopkins University; Lillie, Frank Rattray; Loeb, Jacques; Pearl, Raymond; Protozoan genetics; Publication; Russian politics and science; Travel -- Germany; Travel -- Italy; Travel -- Switzerland; University of Michigan; University of Pennsylvania; World War I -- Impact on science
  - Norton, W. W. and Company, 1930-1945; Correspondence ( 82 items )
    Business; Genetics; Publication; Reviews
  - Pearl, Raymond, 1899-1933; Correspondence ( 278 items )